wonderful we're recording well it's so
nice thank you so and so much for making
time for this session I'm really looking
forward to it and me too
good to be with you what what I like to
rather than me going into a long reading
of a bio I actually like to start with
inviting people to really take the time
to tell a little bit their own story
like what is your point where things
started to shift I mean I know some of
your story which is particularly
pertinent and how did you grow into this
realization that as life we can create
conditions conducive to life and that
regeneration is really our job if we if
we want to reconnect to the wider family
that were part of and that we depend on
so over to you John well sure and again
thanks for the opportunity to to share
this I you know the the the short
version is I spent nearly 20 years at
what I always like to call the old JP
Morgan and you know I was completely
ignorant of any of these issues like I
think most people even today who work in
big finance even with the rise of all of
the ESG and sustainability conversation
that the the understanding of this issue
particularly a regenerative system is
still missing from from from Wall Street
by and large but I you know I worked in
a different time in Morgan it was a very
different culture it was a very positive
experience for the most part and I kind
of left in 2001 really in response to a
nagging itch that I had that had started
many years earlier and the merger with
Chase kind of gave me the opportunity to
leave and and not leave you know my
stock options vested so it was kind of
easy time to to walk out the door and so
I chose to do that just on an intuition
that
but that I needed to find a different
purpose in my life and things started to
happen very quickly after that and
probably the highlight or the low-light
but the most impactful was that I the
first day I went back to the city after
taking the summer off to start to begin
so what's next part of my life happened
to be 9/11 and so I experienced that I I
had a meeting with a charter school CEO
downtown at 9:30 in the morning and I
was thinking about I was doing impact
investing already and I was thinking
about it getting involved in the
education challenge and with a meeting
at 9:30 that means I was in the subway
at 9:10 and so I got to the street in
lower Manhattan right at the moment when
the second plane hit and so that kind of
forced me into this kind of deep think
period and so did to answer your
question I spent the next several years
you know dabbling in various
entrepreneurial projects but mostly
sitting in this building which is in a
converted barn which I set up as a home
office reading books and I'm not an
academic by background and I just
started reading stuff somewhat randomly
and I was sort of a self-select
self-taught PhD and truth and discovered
the environmental crisis read limits to
growth read the food shops work on
systems and it was mind-blowing because
I I kind of came to this rolling
understanding that everything I thought
was true was not possible physically the
physics of exponential growth on a
finite planet don't work and as a
finance guy I know that the economy is
driven by finance and if the economic
premise of our entire global economy is
in conflict with the laws of physics we
have a serious problem and so that
that's essentially how you know it was
just this search for a not an answer to
that question but a pathway to navigate
our way
from that conclusion that brought me on
to this path of living systems and
ultimately the regenerative paradigm so
so in terms of the sequence leaving your
old job was were you already sensing
that there was something amiss with that
system or where you'd only once you took
the time out and you could step back and
had the time to read and growing into
the inside so I was I knew there was
something wrong with the system from a
you know personal fit point of view I
you know I frankly got tired of you know
I went it believe it or not I went into
Wall Street with a fairly idealistic
view that that finance was the kind of
engine of economic prosperity and so I
was going to learn about finance and
then you know I had this idea maybe I'll
work for the World Bank some day and
save the world and and I kind of got
into derivatives at the beginning and
suddenly the purpose of my career was
career success and making money as
opposed to doing something productive in
the world and so I got tired of that and
realized that I kind of I mean I
remember one morning literally looking
in the mirror as I was getting dressed
and not liking the person I was becoming
and I I remember one day you know I was
managing global capital markets
businesses and the big event every year
is when you get your bonus and I
remember handing this trader his bonus
and it was a big number and you know and
it was you know it wouldn't sound like a
big number today given how much people
are making but it was a lot of money and
the guy looked at me and he said
something to the effect of you know well
something I wouldn't say on your
recording I may be only where I could go
and I just said you know my life is not
about dealing with little shithead
traders who you know tell me where to go
when I hand them a big check at the end
of the year and so I just I just
recoiled against the kind of money
culture that Wall Street had become but
that's completely
different than understanding that
economics and finance are in conflict
with physics that's a whole different
level of realization so it was more a
personal you know sort of crisis of
consciousness in my own self I would say
and what let you and to like in terms of
the sequence will said to start up the
capital Institute and then start work on
what was initially the white paper and
then became ya know it was so I left I
left Wall Street in 2001 I always like
to say that because I wasn't there when
the financials and and and it was a it
was years of you know doing impact
investing but kind of wandering in the
in a dark really it was a search it was
my I guess it was sort of my quasi dark
night of the soul where I was really
questioning who I was and what my
purpose was and then the financial
crisis happened and then all of a sudden
my friends who I've been sharing this
with suddenly didn't think I was crazy
anymore
and so I actually created the capital
Institute in 2000 you know I formally in
2010 but I was working on it in 2009 and
launched it in 2010 really as a as a
place to ask these questions and and I
had by then discovered Herman Daly and
ecological economics and was wrestling
with this growth issue but but only
through some of my investment projects
did I just in agriculture did I discover
the whole regenerative basically that
the first piece was discovering holism
in and and I learned that through Allan
savory and and his holistic land
management and we actually created a
company together called grasslands and
I've been on the savory board for 10
years and so I've learned I've learned
about this distinction between
reductionist thinking and holistic
thinking from you know one of the true
practitioners of that
in the world today and Alan introduced
me to yon Smuts who is essentially the
theoretical master of this and it blows
my mind that Smuts his work is still not
it's barely even recognized by folks
means months months was such a
fascinating character I mean maybe not
all of it into today's standards kind of
accolades but he is am the only person
who signed the armistice of both the
first and the second world war and many
know he wrote he wrote was holism and
evolution he kind of wrote maybe in six
months between wars when it wasn't you
know and he apologized in the foreword
for saying you know I didn't really have
enough time to work on this but here you
go and and it's extraordinary and he
came out in 1959 leave and the little
later at the the work that Patrick
Geddes did afterwards was very deeply
influenced by my smarts and and I mean
so much of NATO work yeah he's not fully
recognized yet so support Patrick Geddes
was the founding father of bio
regionalism he yeah you know every day
he lived in Scotland and around the turn
of the century and as a biologist we
also recognized as founder of town
planning and sociology and the Admiral
the Edinburgh Festival is something that
grew out of the N Buress summer school
where heckle Geddes brought people
likely play and heckle and Kropotkin and
all these thinkers together to explore
basically inspired by by unsmooth
specific explore more holistic
perspective on our participation in the
world
yeah cementing character and I think
it's worth sort of drilling down on this
point for a second I I remember when
Allen's first unsavoury first started
telling me you know I said so he's known
for being this guy who says cows are
gonna save the planet
and that's obviously a very
controversial thing to say and I think I
think he probably could have said it
better and I think he was misinterpreted
by what he actually meant but but in
getting to know him deeply remember I
was on a walk with him once and he said
you know my real contribution to society
is holistic decision-making and has
nothing to do with cows and nothing to
do with ranches and and I remember it
was sort of early in my relationship
with him and so I of course those words
are pretty abstract and so I remember
thinking about yeah yeah whatever but
just tell me about this cow thing how
does that work and I I think we are in
the same place in economics and finance
and everything else I mean this is this
this issue applies to kind of every
field of knowledge and and yet it's
something that we naturally don't want
to tackle because it's abstract and and
so if you think about holism and
reductionism in finance I mean there's
nothing more reductionist and finance we
by design optimize risk adjust return on
capital and and and use terms like
internal rate of return which means
internal to that project and external to
the whole system or in ignoring the
whole system so the things we are taught
and believed are our self-evident truths
are actually in conflict with a holistic
worldview and so it's pretty hard to
change someone's belief system once it's
like wired in in in that sense and and
all of the conversations were having
about shifting the economy is shifting
finance always then kind of fall back
into that reductionist logic and you
wonder why we're just making incremental
change and not transformational change
yes now I'm the guy like Alan was to me
who says yeah but we have to talk about
holism and reductionism and everyone go
away no I I mean I've sort of I'm
completely aligned with you because I I
have been countered brainwashed at Omaha
College in the master's in holistic
science into
in 2002 with with a with the kind of
antidote to something that runs thought
deeply through our society that we don't
even notice how often we are thrown back
into reductionist frames and which we
need we just need to know when we're
using them exactly that's a really
important point because that was one of
the things that I started to even kick
back against at Schumacher at the time
because one of the traps we often in
when we try to speak between like about
the value of reductionism and holism
next to each other and is to do the
whole whole pendulum swing paradigm
shift
m-man we're old bad new good and and
rather than get the integration but but
I think that that needs to be excused
impartial partially by it by the
structure of language because even
language has a somewhat either/or
reductionist framing in it at least in
our Western language in a Western
language yeah yeah I mean what West
Jackson has a great saying West Was what
is one of my real teachers and and he
says there's nothing wrong with the
reduction reductionist method so long as
we don't confuse the method with the way
the world actually works and and I think
that's part of holding that balance when
as people wake up to the negative side
effects of an overly reductionist
focused world and particularly you were
saying earlier would finance being
reductionist I mean that the danger that
we even see now among the regenerative
movement of trying to help but in the
process of building the structures like
on the one hand yes we need to value
things beyond financial capital but then
I I often find that the framings around
an ecological capital social capital or
living capital whatever you want to call
it could be so quickly the minute you
create a tool where you can convert one
of these capitals to the other and
ultimately therefore the pathway to
reduce everything to
financial capital and Al you even in the
process of trying to open the umbrella
to say we need to go beyond just valuing
financial capital and return on
investment we need to talk about these
other things and value them the only way
that we seem to be able to value them is
to bring them where every dollar and I
truly believe that many of the people
working on this I'm doing it in a sort
of subversive intended to create that
the vehicle for the largest enclosure of
the Commons yet yeah but if we don't
watch out that's exactly what its gonna
be and and there's there's another
challenge that I've only recently come
to appreciate and that is you know this
is a very practical issue but it's a
very I think significant barrier to real
progress and that is that if you if you
don't operate in the current paradigm
which I would argue you know converting
natural capital into a monetizable of
measurable thing means you can work in
the current paradigm mm-hmm and so if
you happen to like having a job and
making a living you're sort of forced to
do that even if it's subconsciously
because you can then get invited to the
parties you can get invited to give
talks you can invite it to be a
professor you can invite it to work in a
company and work on measuring you know
your ESG stuff but if you reject that
you know it's hard to find a job and yes
we have to just create them yeah but
that's easier said than done and it's
easier said than done it's easier for a
guy like me to say that who spent 20
years on Wall Street then you know my
kids so we're trying to figure out how
to build a career and so I think it's a
very I think we need to be we need to
understand that that's at work here even
if it's at a subconscious level and so
people naturally are going to gravitate
toward what ultimately is
a very sort of subversive hold that the
reductionist paradigm has on our
thinking I mean and the economy I see
this every time when we try to create
the Sabbath Mehta collaborative networks
between different organizations and
where each organization that we're
trying to bring together is a really
valuable organization doing really
beautiful work the potential that they
could unleash if they if the number of
organizations really started to work on
synergy and and transformative systemic
work is enormous but very often being
stuck to some degree in that
degenerative economic system pushes each
one of these organizations
understandably to some extent if look
after their own tribe
then has been doing good work to enable
them to continue to do the good work and
when that's true and safe then they
might be able to invest some extra time
into the bigger story but if they're
kind of with the waterline just you know
they're not going to spend a lot of time
on I'm taking time out to look at the
larger picture of collaboration across
organizations and and the big thing is
it's it's not merging them it's working
with the diversity of these
organizations but bringing them up to
that next level of complexity where they
can can really have a transformative
effect yeah and I mean the the the I
mean you and I've had this conversation
before but I mean the the again getting
back to sort of the the powerful to
powerful role financed plays in this if
you're talking about the nonprofit
sector
you know the fuel there is is is funding
from foundations and you know I was in a
meeting last summer I probably shouldn't
put any names out but I was in a meeting
convened by a philanthropy adviser among
a number of you know large brand name
foundations and and I was there as sort
of the you know everywhere
I was invited was a foundation and I was
there as kind of a provocateur who is a
systems thinker and the purpose of the
meeting was to help foundations begin to
think and behave and operate in a more
systemic way and there's a desire within
the foundation world to do more systemic
work easier said than done
and it's quite it was quite eye-opening
and honestly a bit depressing to realize
how stuck the foundation model is in you
know reductionist problem-solving
show me your problem show me your theory
of change show me what you're gonna do
and then show to me in three years that
you fix the problem and and and that's a
completely different paradigm than
transform transforming systems as you
know I can that's where the fuel goes in
the nonprofit world so surprise surprise
that's what nonprofits primarily are
resigned to doing in order to keep the
fuel I had a very similar experience
also last October where again maybe not
naming where but I wasn't I was in
Switzerland with a large philanthropic
organization that is really doing
wonderful work in in Africa and other
places in in financing community-based
regeneration work and they brought a
number of Dewar foundations like common
land and renature together with a number
of donor foundations and and the donor
foundations all had their kind of
pathway to success how do I like how do
I apply what I learned being a clever
guy in the dot-com industry in Silicon
Valley scale companies to ailing impact
on positive things around the world and
really well-meaning but driving small
organizations on the ground to apply
some kind of California standard
standard of key performance indicators
to their work and in order to be more
effective and scale out more quickly
this this mistaken understanding of the
scale up is what they always say they're
at distinction alone there
bigger is better rather than placed
sourced I mean we both drunk off the
fountain of alpha then the Regenesis
crowd and like that the place forced
working from the uniqueness of place not
copy-pasting solutions but really
adapting solutions to place is so vital
if we want to work regenerative Lee and
none of these foundations get that no in
it actually not only do do foundations
not get that Lee the entire capitalist
paradigm is essentially designed to
dispense with that because that's all
inefficient and economics is about
efficiency and so if we can do a cookie
cutter McDonald's and roll it out
that's super efficient and if we can get
everyone on the Facebook platform that
sure is efficient and and and we can't
be naive because that actually works in
that old context yeah and so it's just
the unintended consequences that we then
cut they come home the chickens that
come home to roost but but this to me is
why you know kind of going back to first
principles is is the only pathway that I
know of to not make those mistakes
because if you if you can if you can if
you can get clear on the principles of a
healthy system mmm no they're not you
know they're not nice to have so there
are actually principles that if you if
you're not in alignment with them you're
not healthy then you have a road map and
without that you have your opinion in my
opinion in jobless opinion man you have
false exam you know false projects that
may show a great project progress in a
you know in a time frame that's
irrelevant like three to ten years but
ultimately be the source of future
problems that are exponentially worse
and if you need an example of that look
at the Green Revolution yeah right I
mean it was a brilliant solution to a
problem and it lasted decades and now we
come and we realize
how profoundly misguided it was hmm and
you think about the probably billions of
dollars of foundation money that went
into the Green Revolution and are still
going into the Green Revolution I'm not
so sure if it ever was really brilliant
because we've we've never actually got
to a point where like it's always been
more than half of the world's people are
being fed by small-scale peasant farmers
most of them are women and and so
sometimes there's a big oversell of what
what the big agro industry actually
managed in terms of feeding the world
and I I think yeah but but but in in the
you know you ask the man on the street
or the informed man on the street or
woman on the street about the Green
Revolution and most people say yeah that
saved billions of people from starving
to death
mm-hmm and there's some truth to that
right so it's not a it's not an absolute
you know anyway but I would love to come
back to the first two things actually
because I'm just imagining you sitting
in the room that you're sitting right
now reading all these books and doing
your deep deep dive and I I must say you
did an excellent job because I had a
moment before I knew you and when I was
probably reading through the pre-final
first draft of my of my book and I did
another search and suddenly there's this
this white paper that pops up from the
Capitol Institute and it's invited well
I I know how to search and and I started
reading it and I had this brief moment
and it's it's kind of internal locus of
control
and a story of initially having that I
can't believe that somebody's put out
something where they've mapped out what
I'm trying to map with my book but they
got it out before me and then I thought
wow wonderful I've just been
corroborated in the maps worth mapping
yeah by somebody else and somebody else
has found the same pieces on and then I
realized that there
and I had some extra and and and since
we've met like very quickly I mean it
was literally I caught myself in that
initial and then it arranged eggs and
then I was like wait a minute what's
this competitive yeah yes and I
immediately kind of applied mudita and
celebrated what what you deceived and
and in in that initial white paper you
were moving your way towards these
principles that you've established for
regenerative economics and tell me a
little bit more about what the
principles I and and and who kind of
gave you the initial impulse to say
that's that must be one of them hmm
well first thank you for your your
compliment coming from you that's you
know that means something cuz you've
obviously thought as deeply about this
as anyone and and I would I would just
throw a little cold water on it by
telling you a quick anecdote so I was at
a regenerative conference once and I was
I've given my spiel about my principles
and my paper and blah blah blah this
very thoughtful smart academic guy you
know
said it said essentially you know John
there's nothing really new here so I
think I think we're all regurgitating
stuff that probably is all rooted in
indigenous wisdom you know if you if you
if you really go down to it what what
we're all saying is what the indigenous
cultures understood and have been saying
but in an language that it's hard for us
to translate into a Western kind of
understanding but you know there's
really I don't think there's a lot new
in my work I if I if I take pride in it
it's that it's a synthesis and an
integration that is put into a
contemporary context for the
contemporary challenges we face and I as
I wrote it I I was always thinking of a
friend of mine his name is Duncan he's a
real person
who is who is a Wall Street guy and I've
always wanted to write in a way that my
friend Duncan wouldn't be able to
eliminate or reduce they were ignored
without going further so it's a very you
know I try to make it sort of something
that that the current paradigm can't
simply reject out of hand
and so my language is is such that it it
will be acceptable but I think the and
and that makes it that limits it to some
to some audiences probably for example
the choice of the word capitalism you
know what I mean by capitalism is is
some integral or integrated
understanding of of multiple forms of
capital but I chose the word capitalism
so that my American audience wouldn't
dismiss this as some socialist no this
is the I'm glad you're saying this
because I've before I heard you say this
um I've actually just justified and
defended you for making that choice to a
number of people because I knew a number
of people who were quite excited about
the initial white paper that was
originally called regenerative economics
and and and then when it came out as
regenerative capitalism they almost felt
betrayed but you hadn't used that word
and I I said to all of them but he's not
talking to you he's trying to preach to
the choir he's trying to build a bridge
into a group of people that really need
to start a conversation around it and
just yesterday I was talking to Alan
Colmes
together with Ken Wilber has developed
the world becomes matrix and the
different levels of human kind of value
clusters looking at the world and and he
again made that point is we're not going
to shift everybody to a consciousness of
interbeing
and and understanding at two years age
guy in cycles like we already developed
mental journey we need to have languages
that address
that the whole spectrum and help people
move on the spiral you might get
something something with you Mike I had
my hand over probably how's that you
know I personally used a word for the
reason you just mentioned and partially
you know if if it was if I were to be
more accurate I would have called a
multi capitals ism but that obviously is
a mouthful
but but actually that there is a you
know I think regenerative economics that
is the core that's home base for me but
there are attributes of our what I
prefer to use the term free enterprise
system that too often get either
dismissed or not even comprehended by
folks in the let's call it the do-gooder
world who've never worked in the private
sector and some of those are very
aligned with regeneration so for example
innovation and an adoption and
adaptation is you know probably at the
heart of the capitalist system and you
know that that it's not enough on its
own but it's pretty easy to sort of
flush the baby out with the bathwater if
we're not careful and so I do try to
sort of have this one foot in both camps
and you know not as many friends in
either camp as I might have if I if I
went one way or the other I know I know
the the yeah I know that then I make
quite well but I think that's what we
need to put Humpty Dumpty back together
again we need to build bridges between
these camps and make people see these
different arguments and and I mean
before we go back to the principles of
regenerative capitalism and where are
you at because right now there's so many
conversations around redesigning
capitalism I mean that even if you see
the difference like I remember working
with guy education and writing their
online curriculum
and particularly on writing the second
version of the economics online
curriculum when when it first came out
and Jonathan Thorson wrote the first
version and we had a critique on the
growth economic system the growth
imperative in the system and and
basically suggested that structurally
you won't change anything if you
structure try its behavior if you don't
change the structure of the economic
system we will continue to exploit each
other and the planet and therefore we
need to redesign economics and that was
extremely radical in 2008 yeah I mean
not that that's was the first time when
it was said people have been saying it
for a long much longer than that but now
you have the founder of the World
Economic Forum as early as 2012 teen
saying the capitalism is broken and
needs redesigning and he even get the
IMF or the WTO and like it's not it's
not a taboo topic anymore to say
something is fundamentally needing a
shift but but but then of course you get
the camp's again of some people say we
can redesign capital as most we can
wreck rescue the world capital if we
apply it in a more nuanced way another
signal or capitalism is the problem and
you get it get kind of George Mumby or
at the moment is on this that this
extreme sort of no there is no
conversation about redesigning
capitalism we need a new system but
ultimately it could be the same thing
we're just getting stuck with language
here again but where you add on that
spectrum well I'd say I mean it's we
talk for the rest of the day on this you
know I it's funny I think most people
would think that I'm like deep in that
conversation because I'm out of that
world and and and the truth is my phone
doesn't ring from the folks that are
rethinking capitalism and and it's it's
partly
I'm viewed as way too radical and and
probably way too theoretical and I I'm
frustrated by this and I kind of roll my
eyes when I see all of the grand the
great capitalists now talking about
corporations need a purpose for example
well what a brilliant idea
you know the the Business Roundtable
last summer came out with this new
statement you know hey how about if
corporations had a purpose and of course
that's the same statement that the
Business Roundtable had as its premise
in 1982 when I started at JPMorgan and
it was only in the I don't know early
90s I think that that Milton Friedman
school sort of took over and they said
the purpose is to maximize shareholder
value so we're now you know in the elite
establishment of the Business Roundtable
which is led by Jamie Dimon who runs JP
Morgan now we're now back to
understanding what was the baseline in
the early 1980s which probably goes back
50 years before that and so you know and
there's a lot of new energy around ESG
and impact investing in blah blah blah
and you know to be honest I rolled my
eyes at it because you know with all due
respect I mean these folks and most of
them are guys are very smart they're
very competitive they're very successful
and because of that in our culture they
have a very big megaphone and so when
when they get up and say we need to
reinvent capitalism everyone says yeah
we need to reinvent capitalism but with
all due respect they haven't sat over
there and read a hundred books to think
about this in a deep way that you and I
have and so there's a lot of
well-meaning and good intention but this
gets back to this issue of not really
getting to two to get your head around
the fundamental profound disconnect
between you know just sort of boils down
to exponential growth on a finite planet
and and you know how many people that
work in business in finance actually
understand what the second law of
thermodynamics says and why it's
relevant to our economy I would I would
bet you if you put a hundred CEOs in a
room and and and didn't count you know
people that worked in a business that
require a physics degree but you know
consumer businesses healthcare
businesses financial businesses whatever
I bet you half of them wouldn't know
what the second law of thermodynamics is
and ninety-five percent of them wouldn't
be able to tell you why that's relevant
to economics and business and so until
people get their head around that issue
where we're sort of moving deckchairs
around and so I you know I wish that my
voice was in that conversation I'd be
lying if I said otherwise but but that
that conversation about the future of
capitalism is pretty locked in you know
at bat at best its we need to
internalize externalities which is a
reductionist way of putting the problem
in the old paradigm and and that's
progress so that's good and that's I
mean it's a massive step and and maybe
it'll buy us some time but that design
won't be the final design and it's
simply not the you know my interest is
sort of Who I am i but the metaphor that
I use for people is that I'm for
whatever reason called and I use that
word intentionally to sort of get in my
little rowboat and row out into the fog
and try to make sense of of all this and
then sort of report back and I'm not
trying to build a career or build fame
about sort of being the leader who
speaks at World Economic Forum and had
and gets the most applause I'm truly
searching for truth in what's the
ultimate crisis and challenge of
humanity at this moment in time and I'm
not going to find it but but that's what
drives me
mm-hmm
I do want to imagine to come back to the
principles I love that you said from the
beginning that like this is nothing new
I've always said this about my work i
synthesize I bring things together
sometimes as a focus Lass's innovation
happens when you connect to things that
were previously disconnected so when you
do synthesis every now and then you
should if there's a spark of something
new that that is also worth sharing but
like I was as you were saying other
people have said this before I thought
of my one of my mentors and elders John
Todd and his friends when they started
the new alchemy Institute in 1969 look
at the the statutes of the new alchemy
Institute what they set out to do and
it's absolutely 100% relevant for what
like if I if I orbit is set up an
organization I would probably use the
same statues of bats well what marching
orders are and but you honed in on eight
principles could you just sum them up
so so I think the most important thing
about my eight principles are really not
my eight principles but the idea of
principles and and one of the things I
learned about the completely about
complexity science and working in
complexity is that we and and this is
again something that is sacrilege in the
business community but we need to accept
that we cannot manage complexity Allan
savory likes to say we need to learn to
dance with complexity and of course
every CEO believes that their job is to
manage their company in a complex
context and so we set up KPIs and we set
up all this stuff and and we end up you
know failing to actually manage
complexity and and it comes back and
bites us in the form of you know a Black
Swan event or a nun you know whatever it
is and and so I think I think the idea
of the idea of principles is that there
aren't there are patterns and principles
of living
that the kind of giants of living system
science you know it's not like they've
all agreed that here are the eight
principles but if you if you were to
show them my a principles or whatever
eight principles you would come up with
there would be this broad consensus that
yes you know these these patterns and
principles roughly describe our
understanding of living systems what you
got there some me going a little bit of
the deep and designed for human and
Planetary health a holistic integral
approach to complexity and
sustainability PhD thesis oh my god well
that's that's the one where I visited
both sides like when the official
version is two volumes because you're
not allowed to print the other side but
I'm pulling it out mainly because in
there and I can I can share the fight
with you I've I pulled together I mean
there's so many principles from the
Rocky Mountain Institute principles and
and in the principles of Dancing with
systems by Donella Meadows and the
leverage points to intervene in a system
also Donella Meadows and and the
principles of Bionic design or you name
it and I've probably got about 50 lists
of principles and yesterday they do all
pretty much converge on what you
distilled out with the eight principles
so in trying to corroborate my didn't
read and nearly as much of that stuff as
you have and you know to answer your
question these came so the first thing
that came to me was this needs four
principles like it's a it's a it's a
North Star it's a roadmap it's and
principles you know I've had this
conversation with a few folks I'm not
sure principles is is accurate you know
maybe the word qualities is more
accurate like qualities doesn't
challenge people to have to you know it
doesn't have this meaning of sort of I'm
declaring what truth is you know it's a
less it's a less aggressive term but
there certainly are qualities like the
fractal patterns of living systems and
like the symbiotic
elation ships that are at work in living
systems that anyone who studied living
systems will say oh yeah that's right
and so the the real issue is to
contextualize them for your purpose and
here's where as much as I meant believer
that there are universal principles for
some reason those universal principles
show up differently in different
contexts so for example I I start out by
saying well I'm gonna use Janine Benyus
'as Jeannie is one of my kind of heroes
I read her book and it's like oh my gosh
this is great
and now all I need to do is essentially
take her her work is largely you know
downstream I was confused upstream and
downstream but you know mostly focused
because it's where a client interest is
in a material design and product isn't
it and so you know part of me as well
all I need to do is shift from that
context to the system design then apply
the same principles because their
principles they must apply yeah but if
you look at her principles and then
think about the context of an economic
system you kind of say yeah you know
it's not that they're wrong but they
don't if you're gonna live it limit
yourself to a finite number of
principles you're gonna want to select
some different ones mm-hmm so but but
again as a friend another friend of mine
says this I think it comes from Buddhism
you know these are all just sort of
fingers pointing at the moon and you
have fingers pointed to moon and my
fingers are pointed I mean my 8
principles are my fingers pointing at
the moon but we can't confuse the
fingers with the moon and so what we're
really trying to do is reduce using a
reductionist method to as as few as
possible patterns principles qualities
whatever work we want to choose that
that allows us to see things through
this regenerative lens and you know each
of these eight principles you know I
could spend an hour talking about each
one because they all operate at many
many different levels so for example
there you know one of them I use is
called rut in right relationship which
is a Quaker term that I got from Peter
Brown he actually wrote a book called
lean right relationship
that that relationship point makes you
know operates at at a unit a planetary
scale the right relationship between
planet Earth and the Sun is the reason
why we have life on this earth and so
that's a that's that's a that's a
quality that is I think manifestly true
and yet it also operates certainly down
to the mic the microscope you know the
cellular level the relationship between
the cells in our body are essential to
our health and if that relationship is
not symbiotic and healthy we can't be
healthy and and if we're living systems
and the planet is a living system why
wouldn't the human economy also be a
living system and why wouldn't that same
quality of symbiotic relationships
operate at the level of the of the human
economy and so you can you can kind of
drill down on each of these principles
individually for hours but the real
power of the principles is not each of
them individually but when they're all
operating at the same time and that's
where it's Carol Sanford and and the
Regenesis folks like to talk about
potential to me that and this is this is
this is a hypothesis not even a theory
although I have seen this work in some
of my investment projects so I'm
personally convinced that it's real but
I couldn't pretend to have the proof of
that in a scientific sense but but but
if we can align our economies and our
businesses with all eight of these
principles at all levels of their
meaning then we unlock immense potential
that exists that we can't see today and
my might be you know if I have a big
idea
it's that exponential growth on a finite
planet as an idea has ended no longer
works at eight seven billion people go
into ten and twelve and the footprint of
the global economy being what it is and
we being in this state of overshoot that
we need to shrink back from we need a
new source of prosperity and the reason
that people won't accept the idea of
limits to growth is because they know in
that means depression so if we're going
to transition the global economy and
survive as a species we need to find
ourselves a new source of prosperity for
not just humanity but all living living
beings we need to figure out a way for
humans to coexist on this planet and be
prosperous however we define that and
you know the the kind of I would say
traditional left-leaning
ideology says oh well we just need to
redistribute wealth and everything will
be good but it's not that simple we
actually need an ongoing source of new
prosperity which is the way living
systems work and and I believe with all
my heart and I'm dedicating my life to
this idea that if we can shift the human
economy into alignment with these eight
principles or something that looks like
these eight principles we will unleash
immense potential that we don't know
exist today and and you know it's
already happening this isn't like some
theoretical thing you know and so one of
the principles is circulation right they
you know any living system has a
metabolism and it needs to circulate and
this is very different than just a
circular economy which of course is
important to efficiently use our
research our scarce resources
this is circulation meaning healthy
inputs into the system robust
circulation into you know all ask all
parts of the system from the top to the
top to the bottom and then an ability to
emit our waste in a way that don't
pollute our nest that's how our
metabolism works so that circulation
also has a level of this the fractal
pattern of cascading circulation like
what circulates at what scale and and
that's that's one of the conversations
that I find a circular economy people
aren't paying enough attention to
despite the fact that their elders which
are really the industrial ecologists and
paid a lot of attention to that you read
the early books on Industrial ecology
the the kind of they say the biggest
punch for the bang for your buck so to
speak if you want to use the old
language
is by regionalizing but the cycles it
becomes less efficient and more wasteful
the minute the cycles get too long and
that's where that bit meets with with
also the double Institute's called from
more by regional economies and yeah I
mean bioregional ideas is you know again
you did you know the source of it better
or not but it it fits perfectly into
this framework so of course there's a
reason why it emerged earlier than it
was then the world was ready for it and
I lost my train of thought where I was
going going through the principles I
mean we can you can also tell people
whether where they find the white paper
so they can look at the principles in
more detail because I knew you're gonna
ask this question I actually if I can I
share my screen you can make sure yeah
just share it and let me see if I pull
the right thing up because I actually
pulled up here we go just so people can
be looking at it while we're chatting
maybe it is
right now mm-hmm there we go ah I have a
pretty graphic right yeah that's nice
but the the the papers on our on our
website on the landing page called
regenerative capitalism how Universal
patterns and principles will shape the
new economy and there's a there's
another paper that is there's also up
there called finance for a regenerative
world which is my attempt to sort of
apply these principles to our financial
system and and and let them lead us
toward what we have to do to change our
financial system so that it's in service
to a regenerative economy and yet I'll
have this all in a book I hope by the
end of this year that would be wonderful
like I've always felt like the white
paper is great but we need your book
just probably the real academic I'd have
a book out by now it's hard to write a
book I wanted to just briefly come back
to two things or three three things like
gee you started with um how people just
get it wrong when like complexity has
become a household term and particularly
when people in leadership positions love
to talk about managing complexity and
and even emergence and all these kind of
things have become popular in language
use but I don't think a lot of people
understand it very well and
unfortunately even to my mind the
complexity science community has um when
it first formed where we're kind of the
old systems theorists met insights from
chaos theory and and created something
deeper and more dynamic with complex
adaptive systems as a port phone and one
of the key insights of the early people
working on this was that complex dynamic
systems are fundamentally unpredictable
and uncontrollable and this goes back to
poker is three-body problem of if you
have more than three interacting
variables interacting with each other
then you mathematically
have a system that is maybe moving in a
strange attractor but but it is not
fully predictable and controllable
limited time frames and limited scale
and so what about what is and I learned
these things from Brian Goodwin was one
of the cofounders of the Santa Fe
Institute was wonderful wonderful man he
was the highlight of my visit to Shamar
College no he's he's yeah well I'm glad
you met him because he he is amazing I
need to go back and read his book yeah
all of them makes you but I mean whether
the early bio
biological ones on quite hard reading if
you're not a biologist but yeah starting
with let that changed his spots and
nature's do they're really wonderful
yeah looks but yeah so slightly do I
think it's the one I've read and how the
leopard change his spots is more focused
on complexity but it's worth reading and
but straight like because we're talking
about but Brian always said that what we
need and in a way that's his framing we
were talking about reductionism and
holism earlier and he he had an another
nuanced way of framing this way he said
we have developed a science of
quantities and and indoors economics and
if it claims to be a science is also a
science of quantities and we only like
the old adage that you hear at nauseam
only what gets measured gets managed
yeah yes it has a point but it's
limiting because what we're actually and
this is why I'm going with like you
mentioned the word qualities and what we
actually want to regenerate and what
sustains the web of life is the quality
of the relationships of the whole
optimizing for all and that nested
wholeness
and M so Brian always said in order to
shift from like that the deep inside of
complexity theory is that the scientific
endeavor of trying to predict and
control the world was a mistaken one and
then we need to be humble enough to
accept our not knowing and uncertainty
is something that will never go away and
therefore to be truly generative and
regenerative we have to keep learning
and keep responding because we're part
of the system and everything we do as as
my friend Gerald meetry professor of a
system signs them at Hull and since
everything is an intervention
we the messed as participants then what
we do or what we don't do each and every
one of us changes the whole M and so
what but but to guide our what Brian
called appropriate participation in that
wholeness
we need a signs of qualities as well as
the signs of quantities so I really like
you reframing the principles which for
me have always sounded a little bit true
hard and to your M get on my bandwagon
and follow my principles I've just come
down from the mountain and here's the
story habits to to something much softer
but actually much deeper and the one
more bit I mean you read some of my work
and you know that I'm a bit of success
with questions and have you seen like in
my book I do
Aikido with your eight principles and I
honored them but I turned them all into
questions but yeah and I read something
recently of yours where you were doing
that and I think it's terrific that I
think they the I don't know it's it's a
it's a tool to to enable a genuine
conversation to take place as opposed to
a you know way I don't know what the
word is a you know a competing idea idea
fest or whatever but I say wherever I
can that the important thing about quote
my principles
is not that they are right but
that they are one man's best effort to
reduce to as few a number as possible a
pattern that we need to get into
alignment with and and that none of them
are my ideas they come from my research
and my experience in working in the real
world and I think the the reason I'm so
passionate about them is that that I've
actually seen the and I could go through
each and every one of these and give an
example and I do in the paper and I'll
do a better job in the book but I've
seen them
not only operate in projects that I've
been involved in but I've seen them in
operation in 50 projects that we've told
the story about where they've just
happened organically or the or the
leaders of the projects have intuited
them and and and never even certainly
never read my paper but never even
thought of them as principles it's just
what they naturally do in response to
the pressures that they are dealing in
and so it's further evidence that this
regenerative economy is an emergent
phenomenon in response to the pressures
of the old system and you know something
as simple as a as a farmers market and
and the whole local food to you know
food to table movement are in alignment
with these principles and that's not
because some you know folks read John's
paper that's because they're responding
to the pressures and the context that's
destroying our food system and so to me
the the proof that they're real is that
they're already emergent in the real
world and and for me the value of trying
to reduce them to language is to help us
all to see this source of future
prosperity and the direction we need to
go and to show where our current
paradigm is completely in conflict with
these principles and so it shows us
where we need to you know focus our
attention to change things and then the
final point I make about them is that it
helps us you know our
so for example the entire you know
quote-unquote sustainable finance
industry is largely centered around this
idea that John Elkington put forth 25
years ago called triple bottom-line the
idea if we need to shift from a sink a
single bottom-line profit and loss
statement to a triple bottom line where
we value planet and people and it was a
brilliant insight and it still holds
truth interestingly John issued a
product recall on the idea let's just
about a year or so ago because he he
essentially realized that it wasn't
working but the entire sustainable
finance industry is largely organized
around that idea and it's now morphed
into big corporations and impact
investing and ESG measures and public
companies and and of course that entire
analysis is the absent sort of a sort of
a check against principles and if we
checked against principles and and I'm
talking specifically about the problem
of the public corporation and public
capital markets so so the premise of ESG
is that if we make the e and
environmental and social and government
governance issues transparent the
markets will solve this problem because
markets you know we believe in a market
system and if markets have the right
information they do their magic you know
Adam Smith's invisible hand well there's
all kinds of unquestioned assumptions in
that theory of change I would argue that
markets or tools markets aren't the
source of our truth and some tools work
better than others in different contexts
but but the problem with the
multinational corporation today if you
look at these eight principles while
there are many problems but probably the
fundamental one is that we have severed
the most important in a capitalist
system their relationship between the
owner of capital and the enterprise is
fundamental
it's as fundamental as the relationship
between the company and its customers
perhaps even more fundamental because
you can always get new customers but you
do have an owner and that relationship
of the owner of capital and the
enterprise is fundamental to a
capitalist system that's going to be
functional and so for example if you
have buildings owned by people who don't
care about fixing the roof you're going
to have leaky buildings and and and bad
housing well what about a multinational
corporation the efficiency of capital
markets has essentially separated the
relationship between the owners of
capital and the enterprise so now
instead of an owner showing up and
saying boy we need to shift our business
model because we're destroying the
planet you have you know anything from a
hedge fund who's in and out of the stock
in a second to a passive you know mutual
fund who is trying to beat the S&P 500
with his stock selection or her stock
selection to an ETF which is essentially
a technology platform that owns a sector
of stocks but you don't have a
relationship between the actual owner of
the capital and the enterprise and you
wonder why ESG isn't actually able to
change the behavior of corporations the
way we need it to and so we've spent 25
years we built an entire industry around
ESG and it's made incremental progress
don't get me wrong I'm a fan of the ESG
but it hasn't dealt with the fundamental
issue that we don't any longer have a
relationship between the owner of
capital and the enterprise the most
powerful and destructive both
constructive and destructive Enterprise
in the history of humanity and there's
no relationship between the owner and
that enterprise and we wonder why
capitalism isn't working
I think you're putting your finger down
something that is really important
honestly I haven't heard it quite so
clearly expressed before and there but
but what it makes me think is that like
I to things like on the one hand I was
just reminded of because you mentioned
John Elkington doing a product recall on
the triple bottom line mmm maybe at some
point
should have a conversation between the
three of us I would love to do - that
would be really interesting to talk to
the two of you together John's on the
regenerative bandwagon now
yeah no no he's the easy I was really
surprised because he actually reached
out to me and we had a couple of
conversations yeah and wonderful man and
I was going with em I first heard him
say that at reporting 3.0 which seemed
to be very aligned with a lot of what
what the Capitol Institute is proposing
yeah those guys are doing great work
yeah and in last year I saw Nora Bateson
also at reporting three point or say
something to a group of people that all
celebrate themselves as positive metrics
and they are really well-meaning people
who are trying to work on shifting the
reporting industry and now even going
beyond reporting um in order to to
effect this conundrum that we're talking
about um and she said something that as
Nora just knows how to do everybody had
been talking about we we can't do with
incremental change anymore we need
transformative change and and then at
the very end of everybody proposing that
transformative changes it was Nora's
turn to ask everybody in the room to say
are we double checking that what we
calling transformative in MA innovation
is gonna make sure that we end up with
butterflies and not with caterpillars
with wings and I think that that image
just brings it down so deeply and and
now bringing that back home to what you
just said and I would like to end
because otherwise we'll probably end up
having a three-hour recording and with
coming home to the question of bio
regionalism because what I heard you say
earlier is that that kind of divorced
multinational corporation where the
owner has nothing to do really in
guiding the the purpose of the
enterprise anyone the owner becomes this
fleeting intangible
is a financial market and is there not
something about applying like like these
principles are wonderful and where's the
what called qualities quality these
these qualities are preferred in right
right relationship and even the image of
that in right relationship on what's on
the screen right now kind of speaks to
that nested wholeness and I think that
well if we are to redeem the word
capitalism and redesign our economic
system in a way that it shifts from
being exploited if and degenerative to
being healing and regenerative I think
we need to pay attention to scales and I
was really delighted when I when I read
in with regenerative communities network
and all that the wonderful network that
the capital Institute has helped birth
with these initiatives around the world
where people are committing to trying to
regenerate economic activity at the bio
regional scale and trying to look into
providing basic human needs and a new
kind of prosperity to people in place
sourced out of place at that kind of
watershed scale and is for me after
spending a lot of time looking at the
community scale and intentional
communities and little experiments of
how do we walk our talk I realized that
you need the bio regional scale you need
a city and there you need small
communities you need ecosystems
it's it's a larger scale at which the
whole system's design where these kind
of principles can really come together
to transform something happens so I
would love for you to just reflect a
little bit on why you think that by
regional scale is important and and also
how would you envision this new economic
to be fractal just like nature is in its
dimension where we of course we will
have global trade and we will have a
global economy but how can we heal that
global economy by regionalizing Andrey
localizing it hmm yeah of course the
idea of local is not a new idea but
local is a it's a it doesn't it does a
disservice to the the profound
importance of of this shift away from
global national to by a regional and and
and because bioregional is where you
know it's where the geological facts a
river system a mountain range an ocean a
coastal plain geological facts that are
not changing anytime soon
well hopefully not come into contact
with human culture so where that the
context here is human economy and
geological facts and the the nature that
they enable and human culture is comes
into contact in a bio regional scale and
and I think when people think about it
wherever you live or wherever you call
home you can get a vision of what's
unique about that place that's different
from other places and if people have a
choice they tend to move to a place that
is either what they know because that's
where they grew up or what they are
attracted to for some you know almost
spiritual reasons some people are
attracted to mountains some people are
attracted to the ocean etc and so to me
it is the sort of self-evident truth
that it is that is where living systems
living human systems are grounded and
our global economy and our global
capitalism and our pursuit of efficiency
has run rough
/ that reality and so you know even the
idea and I'm not telling you anything
you don't know but the idea of a
nation-state grew out of a different
paradigm has nothing to do with how do
we operating in right relationship with
this living planet it had to do with
forces of power and and and you know
very kind of competitive paternalistic
and and I often say if you just look at
most of us can do this to just close
their eyes and imagine the map of the
world with the nation-states and it's
all straight lines by some colonial
power literally done with the ruler
saying this is mine this is yours it has
no biophysical reality but we have a the
regenerative communities network which
is a you can find a link to it on our
website but also just google it we use a
visual of a beautiful color if I was
good I could pull this up quickly but
it's a beautiful color visual of
Watership of a watershed map and there's
another zooks I can probably pull it up
quickly when I'm chatting but anyway
there's that brilliant because you you
can see the the watershed context of the
whole planet and where it aligns with
nations and where doesn't and so any
rate the to answer your question you
know one of our principles is this idea
of honoring community in place and and I
use the word honor you know by intention
obviously and again this is sort of
humans being humble to the greater
essence and and nature of place that
exists whether or not were there you
know and and you know Wendell Berry has
this beautiful expression I see as he
only he can do he says there's no such
thing as a unsay credly
there's only sacred places and
desecrated places
and and so I think you know partly as a
practical way to get our hands around
this challenge if we if we try to
operate on a global scale or a big
nation scale it's too much it's too much
for me to hold in my head mmm I work and
we now have I don't know there's
probably 15 active by original
initiatives and I've been around most of
them I see all these same patterns and
principles showing up I see the same
quality so whether you're on an island
off of Newfoundland in Canada or in the
rainforest in Costa Rica they all look
the same to me now this this emergent
regenerative community regenerative
culture is is the same in these
different contexts but it's not the same
as a practical reality obviously a
tropical culture is going to feel very
different than an Arctic culture and an
Arctic economy but that's why the
qualities or the patterns are so
important and and if you look at each of
these initiatives through a regenerative
lens you see these same qualities
appearing in their own unique context
and so you know I like to say every
snowflake is unique but every snowflake
looks like a snowflake and what my hope
is in linking these initiatives together
and by the way you know you could you
could you could identify a PhD thesis
they could write a paper or a book on
thousands of bioregional communities
that are emerging and expressing these
regenerative qualities their whole I
just looked on in Egypt called psyche
yeah I mean basically just within the
global eco village Network and the
influences that each one of these older
eco villages had on their region whether
I'm thinking of the more a shia region
around fintan i or the region in
Pondicherry around
Oroville in India or even the region
around Tamera and Portugal that they're
transforming having had that nucleus
where people are exploring the
different way of being with the world
has had influence in the wider region
when they when they there for long
enough now the problem today is that
they're all largely diffused and
disconnected and therefore invisible to
quote the mainstream who's going to
Davos and talking about economic growth
and doing all the stuff that we do and
and this this is my hope and dream it
mayor name may not be a good idea but
but you know following Margaret
Wheatley's work the way living systems
take change to scale is through this
networking through scaling out and
replication and she's got a brilliant
little short paper I don't remember
what's called but she wrote it with
Deborah freeze and it talks about naming
this thing so we're naming it the
regenerative communities network you can
come up with a better name if you like
connecting it so make sure that these
these initiatives are connected and so
that there's this learning shared
learning happening illuminate it so
shine a light on it tell stories about
it show that it's a thing as opposed to
a disparate group of projects it's
actually one thing and then and nurture
it and illuminate it so you know it
needs it needs care and feeding and so
our hope is that each of these
initiatives will and here's where
capitalism comes back the the
transformation from degenerative
extractive economies to regenerative
economies will require investment of
real real money real stuff real projects
from solar panels to regenerative
agriculture to you know buildings that
house cool little startups etc and and
imagine if we can create you know and
again in shifting back into old finance
language an asset class where the
projects are de-risked because they
emerged out of the right relationship in
a bio region mmm-hmm and the capital
then once it understands that this is
future will understand that their
current investments are at higher risk
of of collapse certainly you know the
obvious example is in fossil fuels but
it's happening you know the entire
capital markets are priced to
exponential growth and when the world
wakes up that that game is up the entire
capital market paradigm is going to have
to collapse I'm afraid and so capital
will be looking for you know let's call
again an old language low risk low
return places to deploy capital to
create real value and to preserve
capital for the investors and our hope
is with the regenerative communities
network that by then this network will
have matured from 15 initiatives to 1500
initiatives and that they will have kind
of scaled out in their bio regions so
that they'll have critical mass and that
they'll be able to t it's a sort of T up
all of these things that are going to
help all these projects that will help
transform them into a regenerative
paradigm and capital will be hungry to
find such projects but if we do it in a
disparate way where everyone's doing
their own thing all over the world
unfortunately these tools of capital are
highly concentrated and so you have the
problem of well that's a really nice
little project there mr. Fullerton but
you know I've got four billion dollars
and if you want me to invest forty
thousand dollars it doesn't that's not
worth my time to read your memo this was
so fascinating thank you for this
because I now really understand the
deeper strategy behind the regenerative
communities Network thank you no thanks
thanks for that and and I've also
realized that there is this parallel
because you know that like I mean the
cat'll Institute isn't most in this as
well this initiative that I started to
birth out of the frustration of the mush
Spring Prize judges who had come
together for a number of years always
having to choose out of 50 51 finalists
from all over the world small wonderful
projects clay source projects doing real
regeneration a lot of them ecological
some of them social all around the world
and and we had I mean wonderfully
generous from lush we
two hundred and ten thousand pounds to
give away to 11 projects em which is a
nice thing too to be able to do but it's
peanuts of money and the frustration of
choosing out of these 50 was always
extremely high and what was born out of
that was the conversation of how do we
give more value to all these runner-ups
that have already gone through a due
diligence processes and have been
checked on by the people from the
ethical consumer magazine the last staff
than the judges and how do we a showcase
them to the world make them visible to
each other so they don't feel alone in
in their in their struggle and showcase
them to possible funders and in that
conversation which is matured with now
the Buckminster Fuller Institute in the
capital in voter has the same name what
the Bucky fuller prize yeah exactly
that's that's what like I I said too
much we're not the only ones who are
running a prize where the front end is
cheaper than the back end so it costs
more than we give away and then we end
up with all these these runner ups that
that have been vetted but nobody's
giving value to that and so that's why I
suggested let's let's talk to battements
the fuller they must have exactly the
same problem and now this has evolved
into the regional rasa tea platform that
hopefully will be launched soon and that
is brilliant
you know what we need to do is that so
there's gonna be interrelationships
between all that all of those projects
and let's say there's you know there's
got to be let's just put a number
there's got to be a hundred projects in
those databases and there are viable
thriving things that should be scaled
out and replicated and and maybe it's a
thousand but it's probably at least a
hundred and and imagine if then they
were the the kind of the flywheel or the
engine to build co-benefits within each
of their bio regions so that they're
again not isolated projects working in a
great big wide world on their own but we
harness the energy that they're throwing
off already into bio regions so they
so that we get this amplifying effect
out of bioregional scale that's that to
me is the you know that the hard thing
is to build a flywheel once you get a
flywheel going it gets much easier to
build on it and and and flywheels
usually take courage and creativity and
capital and guts and sweat and tears to
get going so what we need to do is find
the flywheels that are regenerative and
then you know throw energy at them which
is people and and money and expertise
and help them to spread that energy in
their bio regions and then the
bioregions start exchanging with each
other and then you essentially before
you know it you've got your new you've
reinvented capitalism
you've got the regenerative economy
that's operating at a bio retail scale
and then the politicians will wake up
and say oh there's something good going
on over there why don't we settle
policies support that stuff rather than
supporting you know subsidizing fossil
fuels well I had a conversation with
James quill again who has been advising
like we eat on the one hand did this
wonderful study of the the bio region of
the San Francisco watershed but as a
political adviser I mean he's been
advising governments all over the world
for his whole career and he's also had
some work with um the IMF and even in
the corridors of the IMF I won't say who
people have actually said show me the
example of a viable bioregional economy
at and and vibrant by regional economy
and its patterns and we need to shift to
support this but wait so we need to just
create to make these things visible if
you if you stop sharing your screen then
I've just had while you were talking a
bit of a fiddle and lost control and
then I be able to just see then I share
this I work and yeah and I can share
this briefly what's now you can't see
you see this beautiful everyone that's
Robert zukes yeah he's a geographer and
he this is real scientific data of
basically the world's fire regions huh
what the word watershed watersheds
watersheds in here like you can see the
Mississippi watershed the Amazon
watershed here and the Nile this is
whole this green thing is the Nile
watershed and of course they're they're
very large and some of these so my sense
is that some of these mega watersheds
might might feasibly be divided into sub
bio regions within the watershed
I mean bioregions is a loose term as I
understand it it doesn't have a firm
definition you sort of know it when you
feel it kind of thing but they if you go
back for a second one thing I'd like to
point out about the United States and
the Mississippi the Mississippi River
yeah our region or watershed which is
massive if you think about what we've
done as an economic model in that bio
region it's essentially extracting it's
it's an agricultural extraction economy
yeah and it it has been transformed to
industrial agriculture and I'm making
generalizations here it's not totally
true but broadly speaking that's the
breadbasket of the United States because
that's where the the you know the the
plains of the Mississippi River system
are and we've we've you know by design
converted that into industrial
extractive agriculture and I have it
when I give talks sometimes I have
another map which shows the red state
blue state split in the United States
and and the red state the red states
line up pretty pretty much not to the
tee but pretty much up against the
Mississippi River watershed well so why
is it a surprise to us that you know the
you know the red state which to me has
nothing to do with conservativism and
liberalism it has to do with desperation
you know subsistence living under under
a very extractive system that has gone
all the profits have gone to a very few
you know massive agricultural companies
and destroyed communities and the
environment systematically in the
process on a massive scale
you wonder why that's all now you know
Trump country so this is like not a joke
this is what happens when you
systematically turn a region a bio
region into an extractive project now
the reverse is also true
imagine if that entire bio region was
converted to regenerative agriculture
that would mean that the ignoring that
the Great Plains which are this massive
carbon sink but have been converted to a
carbon source would be reverted to a
carbon sink and and we'd have healthier
food and healthier people and
sequestering carbon and and less floods
and blah blah blah it would transform
that entire region which wouldn't
transform the politics of the United
States which is one of the biggest
problems of our world right now and and
I think the the the idea of rewilding in
that area would also have a lot of power
particularly like getting Ted Turner
involved he's got a few PI's of spare
and rewilding some of the Great Plains
but you know people don't realize what
we did to the Great Plains is as bad
perhaps I'm not an ecologist to judge
but it's certainly of the comparable
scale of badness as what we're doing in
the Amazon right now hmm we're tearing
down the Amazon to make room for
industrial meat feedlot systems and
we've already ripped up the northern the
great prairies which are these massive
perennial carbon sinks and convert them
to corn and soybeans to feed cattle hmm
so what's the difference and why aren't
we up in arms about what we've done in
the Great Plains the way we're up in
arms about burning down the Amazon we
should be we should be well this has
been super rich and I feel like we could
easily continue
for another hour and but I know that if
we post a video that is 2 hours nobody
will watch it and I won't have time to
get into kind of editing it into nice
bite-sized chunks as people like to feed
on these days but this has been really
nice and maybe we can do it again
because there's just so much talk about
we need to we need to come over to my
Orca and set up a regenerative community
there to join the network because I mean
I'm still very much working on that I
just don't feel I mean I've been in a
way I've been working on that before the
capital Institute was around the time
that since the capital Institute was
formed and before the regenerative
communities network was formed but it's
it's interesting because just a couple
of weeks ago I had a public talk here on
my Orca where that the topic was the
potential for Majorca to be an example
of by regional regeneration and how
islands are special cases within buyer
angels because they even better defined
boundaries and and that actually enables
a lot and then of course Majorca is a
sub case where the economy is so
dependent on tourism that you have to do
a sort of turning the problem into the
solution I keep with the system if you
want to change anything on my Yorker you
have to also ask the question what would
regenerative tourism look like how could
tourism give back to a region but then
suddenly that idea that it's already
nice to have a case study of this size
and that has global significance but
when you when you put it into the
context using this as an exploration of
how tourism big it can become the the
flywheel the the motor for the
transition not for the final output but
really for the transition of re
regionalised in production and
consumption and building the healthier
structures at the local scale and doing
eco systems restoration work then M this
little island suddenly could have global
significance because M that's what's
needed and so many paradises around the
world and on top of it because Majorca
once exported one level like one model
of tourism all-inclusive mass tourism to
the world and may York and Families
owned five of the 20 largest tourism
companies in the world that the
family-owned businesses by my Yorkin
that still have a patriarchal structure
basically it's five guys you need to
convince that you should do it again
they should in their age export the new
model of tourism called regenerative
tourism to the world to redeem the sins
of the first engine that they and that
sort of that the narrative that I'm
trying to seed and at this meeting two
weeks ago we just realized that there's
so many pieces in the puzzle and so many
players that like some of them before I
even came to this island I mean there's
a lot of beautiful local leaders who've
done amazing work already and and I'm
just teaming up with a with a filmmaker
to begin to tell this story and make it
visible to itself because I think that
so much of the work that we need to do
at this bar regional scale coming back
to complexity like if you if you can't
predict and control the system and you
have to have the humility that you
interacting with it in your own
ignorance and in your own best
intentions guided by the qualities like
that you distilled and then then you can
really understand that working with
complexity and trying to merge your
positive emergence is about who speaks
to whom the relationship of that
conversation the quality of that
conversation so basically whose connect
how's the system connected to itself the
quality of the relationships and the
quality of information flow yeah already
it changes everything and after that
then comes the quality that the
financial flows and the resource flows
and all that but but that's what we need
to do it at both in the fractal of the
bio region and then also by a region two
by region as you just described is is
very much the process
that we you know we don't enforce it but
there is a there is a you know a cycle
of engagement that each of these
regenerative community networks in a
sense sign up to do and the first one is
to convene and and learn how to see
itself as a system the way you just
described so there's stuff we can learn
again every snowflake is unique but
every snowflakes are snowflake what they
did in Fargo island on the north coast
of Newfoundland is totally relevant to
what you're doing and talking about a
Morocco thank you we're actually
thinking about running as soon as tech
talk like event where we invite all the
people who hold a piece and have done
good work transformative work on the
island to present their little piece of
the puzzle and then keep them for
another day to have a conversation of
how do we put our pieces of the puzzle
together and then there would be the fun
if you convene that meeting you will
have you will be introducing people into
each other who are already working in
this paradigm but never knew each other
I never knew what you're doing is sort
of like what I'm doing that's what
that's what that's been part of my
weaving over the last 10 years I think
that like that the time is right now in
in Majorca to take that next step but I
have to sync it also with my own kind of
personal you know not wanting to be away
from that maybe too much anyway in that
I need to go in quality it's all in
balance so thank you so much for this
time it was really nice and all the work
that you're doing in the world it's it's
very important and you're doing a great
job and synthesizing this and getting it
out into the world well likewise and
takes one to know one
and regeneration rising trim tabs unite
that's okay well